welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
cloud you can begin whenever you want
but
yeah don't you want to say your thing i
like it i like hearing you say it to be
honest
okay i always bastardize okay welcome to
the stoa
the stoa is the place to cohere in
dialogue
or deco here as it turns out uh
in some favorable way in dialogue about
what matters
most at this moment this
pinpoint of a moment the spot
right here right now
okay that's my version peter doesn't do
it quite that way
uh yeah so um
welcome thanks for returning some of you
keep coming that's really nice some of
you are new
so it's always a little bit of a design
problem because in some sense we've
built some coherence and capacity about
what we're doing
but we try to make every session stand
on its own
so but for those of you who are new
and please ask questions if you get lost
in the weeds there's a lot of weeds here
we plant weed seeds they grow faster
they don't have to water them so much
it's not so much
maintenance um so
last week we did uh we worked with poems
that act like cohens and
[Music]
um
thinking we should do uh we might do
a little more of that today but is there
something
that uh some idea or experience or some
nagging irritation or some
deep question
or something that's arising in you that
has a lot of energy we could just uh
start there it's as good as starting
anywhere
so does anybody have or comment
um yeah
actually could i take you up on your
offer from the beginning of last session
about some sense making around
a lot of stuff going on in america right
now um
just yeah i was just wondering what your
take on
like why suddenly there's this like
attention and visibility on issues of
racism and policing and like kind of
stuff going on there
like it's really you know it's become
very um
very visible to a lot of people and
there's a lot of talk around it i'm just
wondering what your take
that was yeah um
i do not really i mean i have some ideas
i can share them out after i say
what i want to say i don't really know
why uh
things come and go in the popular
imagination
um you know we went from covid to uh
george floyd really quickly i mean part
of the reason obviously is because it's
so
horrific the video is very simple you
know what i mean it wasn't like
nuance whether somebody was actually
resist you know they're there but
there's also been i remember one
of um the woman who was
you know the pregnant woman stunned in
her car there's other than other videos
that weren't simple
either i would suspect a lot of it has
to do with the energy
of um being locked down
you know those these energies don't go
away um
but if they leak out they don't tend to
kind of
create a threshold event um
my opinion about it is i i actually
um now you know this is nuanced so i
agree with
a lot of the information ecology
but looking at it i think there's a lot
of positive
aspects to it i think the discourse
especially from some black women that
i've seen
is is pretty sophisticated and
it's a kind of across a broad spectrum
of inter interpretation
the number of people globally that have
uh been inspired by this
is is truly inspirational there's been a
lot more like boots on the ground
than looting uh although the looting
gets
you know can get a lot of
a lot of uh reaction and and we also
know that it's not always clear who
starts the looting or how
how that's escalated um
i think you know what's very interesting
is i see blm as
maturing somehow some of the
conversations is much more mature than
it was when it first started
uh so that's a good thing um
uh and i think some people might uh
experience that is being watered down i
don't know you know you always have that
that aspect of it too
um
you know do you know these guys blogger
heads
i'm not going to remember that i'm not
going to say the names right
they're two black american intellectuals
uh one's economists from brown the
others
a linguist from colombia
and they uh they have a they have been
having a blog for a long time called
bloggerheadstv
they will seem very conservative to
uh liberal leftists um
but i think that uh
if if you want to get a sense of the
kind of
dialogue that interests me um
you should listen to their last couple
of
uh podcasts
i don't i feel uncomfortable uh
expressing an opinion
about this large of uh
event of this large significance because
i always feel strange to try to speak
for the black experience or split
to the black experience now if you and i
were hanging out that's one thing we
but if you're asking for me to be some
kind of like
public authority um
i very much more would
like you to listen to uh
black people who have had that
experience can contextualize it and not
project
over it now i did have a conversation
with future thinkers which was a little
transparent that'll come out
um and it was more like us just talking
to each other and less like
uh authority um
so yeah if you can
i'll um i'll
uh find that link before we um
leave today and um i'm not saying i
agree with everything that they're
saying
uh sometimes uh black intellectuals
seem quite uh conservative to me
especially
in terms of their economic ambitions
um so it's not not like i'm saying i
agree with them
but it's closer to the kind of
conversation that i think is important
around the periphery of what's happening
also in the mainstream the mainstream
event
is the catalyst for these other
conversations
but in many cases the mainstream event
does not have
a mature discourse but that's happening
elsewhere
okay so um um
i don't know did i answer your question
without feeling like too much of a
cop-out and you could call me out if you
want to
you want a specific opinion that's
that's cool
that's the thing i wasn't again asking
yet for the big public
um yeah bigger kind of position on it
but just yeah last week you kind of made
that offer and yeah i was intrigued
um by you know what yeah
so yeah thank you for sure yeah i find
myself being tugged sometimes
like um um oh you know i have to check
for confirmation bias
i uh sometimes um you
so so let me put it in a broader thing
of how i surf the
surf the sense making scene
sometimes i have very strong opinions
you hear my strong opinions where i have
them here
uh but when i'm just trying to figure
out like what's the what's the
collective sense making happening
one of the things that happens is uh um
and you should listen for this amongst
the
people we legitimize uh in these these
forums
um self-organized collective
intelligence is not like collecting
intelligence sorting it through and
figuring out what narrative works
right self-organized collective
intelligence
operates at the collective level like
your brain operates
like when you try to make a decision you
have a little bit maybe a
little bit of one of you wants to go
visit your mom and a little more wants
to stay home and a little
you know you have many different things
operating at the same time
you have local wisdom you have you know
bigger ideas
and even the minority positions
make a difference right so if you have a
small reticence to act
100 in one direction then the way you're
going to language your opinion in that
direction will be
held back a little it'll have a nuance
so when we are looking at the collective
intelligence
of the country let's say
you want to allow in
all the anecdotal information all the
real information okay not the
not the there's bots creating fake news
and stuff
so that you will and you'll get a sense
that
where we are at is 85 here
5 there 12 there and that's who we are
not just the 85 or not just the
mainstream or the official conclusion
that's a reduction of the information
ecology
right so um
so when people pay attention to
like let's say commentators that i don't
agree with
but if there's a they may say oh i don't
agree with them but they paid attention
so that shifts them slightly
and everybody's slightly being shift and
you get the behaviors that represent
the sum total of all that's in that's in
the information ecology at the same time
so you see this with how things start as
conspiracy theories and maybe they're
not 100
right but they start to shift what
people investigate
and then they start to get more
information and then the story
and the opinions mature over time
and a lot of this has to do not only
with facts
in the time that it takes to gather
facts but the energies in the spirit
in which in the context in which those
facts
or anecdotes can be said right so in a
certain context
um this is a principle from collective
insight practice in a certain context if
you think
i'm uh being competitive with you
and then you call me out you're saying
you just want to prove me wrong
there's a certain point at which i ca
doesn't matter what i say
if i say no no no that's not the case
you'll just
think i'm passive aggressive like once
you're kind of in this context or the
structure
there are times when nothing you can say
will actually
forward your authentic meaning
parents have this with children all the
time especially teenagers
you know you can't just like when you're
teenagers going through these
stages where they just want they just
can't see you
it doesn't matter what you say you know
you can even say look i know you're in
pain it doesn't matter what i say
and even that will get sucked into their
interpretation
right so in these cases it's very
important to understand
the context in which what you say is
held
and can you actually deliver your your
message
and if you can't then this is a perfect
time to practice stoicism
because what ends what's important in
the end is the behaviors you elicit
not whether you've convinced people you
were right and you knew it before anyone
else right this
we have this impulse to want to speak
what we think is true as soon as we
think it's true so
in case we uh in case we're right before
everybody else you know
um so it's always a matter of
how are you inhabiting the space how are
you shifting the energy
what behaviors are going to be amplified
when i
when i've had my say um
and and what matters what matters most
to you
and that's a dialogue you have to have
with yourself
you know um
years ago i was in a house in oakland i
mean in
berkeley oh no this is when i was in san
francisco
and we we hosted the
zimbabwean liberation army
because they would they would have these
meetings in the communist
center in oakland yeah there's we had a
house full of people running around
walkie-talkies and guns and
and a lot of uh
activist slash revolutionary
energy and um
i remember not being able to like really
process
that you know i remember
when i look at the invitation now it
feels like
there was me i had these ideologies and
i was quite naive
because when they came i guess
you know i guess they i thought they'd
be more like me
this is you know when i was like 23.
i thought they would be more like me and
they were there were
they were um
you know they were serious
revolutionaries that were really serious
um i just tell the story because
just one anecdotal evidence of like
pay attention to how you actually
experience things
um that's a truth that should live in
the space too
uh thank god knowing that you know
nothing happened nobody got hurt or shot
or
you know it was very overwhelming it was
very overwhelming
to on the one hand have an ideology and
then to
feel that disconnect you know
experientially that was not
that was not me it was quite
ideologically driven i
i'm happy we did it it was really a
great learning experience
um
but yeah so practicing the stoicism of
um really understanding the context are
you in the context or you're outside of
the context
really you know not what you're supposed
to be
oh you're supposed to be in this context
i can feel that
and feel that i'm not in that context at
the same time
in my courses we move from what you
should do to what you could do
okay yeah i hear what i should do but
what
what what it what can i do what can i do
and i think i'm at one of the first uh
a couple times back on this and this
program or whatever this thing is
this thing we're doing um
i cautioned uh
that some of these sense making uh
programs you know a lot of them are
white male over certain
demographic and
you know the question is is it theirs to
do
is the revolution or the emergent future
is it
is it i think i was talking about even
western culture is it ours to do
like we we just go straight ahead like
oh my god i get really serious because
you know this is ours to do well it
might not be ours to do
it might be you know um
african young teenage african women
we we don't know you know so just having
to zoom out and being reflexive about
your own motivations and intentions
um yeah and i i get like that someone
called me out on twitter the other day
because i was excerpting something
i was writing and i was going we this
and they said
who's the we and i said who's the way
and i said of course
i'm speaking for all of humanity i have
an affliction to write like that you
know
so uh that's kind of how public
intellectuals write you know um
but what's really interesting and what
i'm starting to
work with a group of women who are
thinking of coming out publicly
is how do we move from an information
ecology
that collates information i mean i think
we need that
but uh
like what happened to anecdotal and
parochial
knowledge right so we've been trained to
uh put aside our anecdotal knowledge
put aside our parochial experience
because it doesn't match the mainstream
uh opinion and we discount it
you know um so this came up because
someone because of coded lockdown moved
from
brooklyn to a farm and started growing
vegetables and she said
like she's noticing all these things and
she said but i always read this
and i always read that and i'm like yeah
because what you're reading
is this collation of who knows
narratives or something
and now you're starting to use
perception and you see it's not the case
and good for her because what happens is
when we download
official scripts whether they're liberal
whether they're conservative whether
they're
for social justice but when we download
this official scripts
we can no longer actually see what is
actually happening
we literally can't see it um when we
take
media for actual experience we're making
a mistake
right so we have to relate to the media
we consume as media
not as a window to our actual experience
right so um you need to go meta
always go meta on media in this
information ecology
because it's not actual it's an
experience of
consuming media it's an experience with
media it is not a portal on the actual
experience itself
and that's how we need to relate to it
and the question is how can we use this
technology so
we're tapping into
this other way that has been kind of
discounted
and and so for example um
the difference between we hear a lot
about
mimetics and alternative narratives
finding the narrative what narrative is
important
people talk a lot about we need a new
story right all of this
right this is in this whole space
um maybe that's not the right approach
we don't need a new narrative we don't
need a new story we don't
need a new like ideology
we need spaces where people can show up
and tell their story
their anecdotal experience
and let it live for what it is you don't
have to attach it to an ideology or a
movement or whatever
but this is just the kind of information
these spaces lock
out
because the private experience will
never
match the public expression
because the public expression is a
generalized
illusion
so how do we and this is why
you know i was talking to peter a little
bit about this this is why the women in
my group
don't want to come out because the the
actual events in their lives matter
and if they talk about experience they
had with their child
there'll be five different narratives
coming at them you should have done this
you should have done this you should you
know
it's not possible for people
in this ecosystem to be interested in
their own anecdotal evidence
so why not for example i said i did an
experiment on facebook before i
i left it i said
oh you know my sister's hospital there's
nothing going on they're laying
everybody off
i i can't tell you how much
hatred there was on that thread
because i said that
it was not allowed for that to live in
the information ecology
now other people said you know we can we
can talk about this
what there's a possibility for example
if you look at cause and effect it's
very complex
and that sankova is not real but did we
do we have the appropriate response to
these kinds of things
and the response was for example in new
york which we knew was gonna you know
these urban centers get hit hard the
response was
centralization one or two hospitals
received all the equipment and all the
uh
people and extra um nurses
and so when you were out in the
periphery
if you got covered you went to these
hospitals
which caused overwhelm of the hot very
it fulfilled the prophecy our hospitals
in the northeast were
und over in general overall if you took
them off
take all they were under exploited
but because we centralized the covid
emergencies to a few hospitals
we got the impression the media wanted
to see
our relationship to the nursing homes
was literally horrendous
right here you have people stacked on
top of each other
often in not nice conditions the food
you know if you've been to the
nursing homes have really deteriorated
high-risk population
and the staff just walked in and out
but that's a that was a simple call
that was a simple call you have to be
elon musk
to understand the complexity of that and
we didn't pay attention
we made this big about you know cuomo
and this
so the idea is try to think
in practical terms um honor your
local experience honor your anecdotal
experience and your parochial
relationships understanding that they're
not general
you know you don't want to mistake them
for the whole try to
get more of that into your information
ecology
and relate to information your
experience with information
is experienced with information not a
portal to the actual experience
that was kind of a long download but
i kind of working it out myself over the
last few weeks
so thank you because it was helpful for
me to try to figure out
what some of the principles i'm trying
to develop are
and and to be honest with you that you
know i have that sense of
it's a capo you know i can feel that
implicit in the situation right now is
people want
someone to take a stronger stance on one
side or somewhere
and i'd be happy to do that
in an actual conversation
offline with with people have the actual
experience
but all i can provide is my own
it's not a formula for the context of
the whole
i appreciate that thanks yeah
and you know then i could ask you the
same which would be fantastic
right like wow oh my god you know like
i'm sure i'd be very
really surprised i have no idea
i can feel myself projecting how how
how cool it would be to hear from your
perspective
uh but i think that's that kind of those
kind of conversations are really
exciting um
unnecessary and you know people are
having them
offline and sometimes online
maybe
maybe not i don't know
now what we've been trying to do here is
is more like develop skills or
you know uh yeah it's a playground
there's like
there's like jungle gym and then there's
this merry-go-round thing and then
there's
this and then that and we're just
trying to do that but yeah i think it's
something that people
are trying to to how do we how do we
expand the potential of this technology
um i think there's been a first wave
um
there are people that i consider experts
um like in
economy i like to listen to mark blythe
again from brown all these
people are from brown it's actually
brown
and um and and um
these two other guys lowry i can't
remember love
love something anyways um yeah
so um let's see what we have in the chat
okay yeah let's see we have some
powerful voices
um yeah
good question is there something else or
some feedback on that did something
sound question you mentioned
a couple of phrases you mentioned
download the script for instance
and i've been reflecting on this idea of
cosmology
as part of metaphysics and i'm starting
to see a lot of
computer based cosmological assumptions
coming into the discourse so i wanted to
get a sense
of hey how do you think about this
cosmology of your own
your personal experience do you just
copy paste it from say
taoist buddhist or stoic cosmology or
is it something else and b how does one
reflect on this because that seems to be
the main meta context based on which we
keep interpreting
the events and keep making sense of
things and so on
yeah so those are like your mental
models
what's the script at the level of mental
is that what you mean like uh
so for instance like if i if i break
down the metaphysics as ontology
epistemology and cosmology like within
that
how do i not take a pre-formulated
cosmology
into the world be that of modernist era
postmodern or now meta-modern
yeah how do i formulate an organic thing
which is
adapted to me sorry this is completely
off attack no no no no no don't we just
we just follow the squirrel
watch out where your squirrel runs right
you just
follow the squirrel you'll get to the
nuts uh
so first of all i'm going to answer your
question
but first of all there's an insight i
had
on the one hand i do write about this
and i'm currently writing about it i
write as if
what a person says is embedded in
something like their cosmology
okay uh now um
that's not that's actually true
people people segment all kinds of
beliefs
so it's not always true that these these
larger pictures are these mental models
at that level epistemology cosmology
governs how they make sense of things
um does that make sense you want me to
unpack that or just make sense
like like my mom was an emergency room
nurse a head
charge nurse but she believes in god and
and if she goes into her cosmology she
doesn't believe in science
or evolution so they s
they live in and when you ask her well i
used to torture her by like really
pressing her
her it's literally like she goes
blank
her her mind can't make the connect that
she can't
she can't see one from the other they're
like they live
separately and literally people's minds
go blank because she tries
trying really hard but there's like a
point at which
like there's no more sugar left or
something so
we don't want to make the mistake that
for for everyone i think for
for people who who are reflexive
we want them to we want the stack to be
coherent right
we're trying to say well i want my this
to be coherent but this is not
it doesn't seem to be the case for most
people
um even even people who could you know
use my mom an example
uh but even people with more
sophisticated cosmologies and stuff
these things seem to be able to live
in different parts of our brain
but um my cosmology so
i have different levels like when i
teach
and i'll say this to my students
especially early on
if we're talking about evolutionary
anthropology we have one module on
evolution
i have to say well we're just going to
enter in this model
it's relatively mainstream it's a
starting place if you know if we want to
move off of it
but we're just going to use evolutionary
anthropology
and it's not it's not really hard uh
uh evolutionary biology like eric
weinstein
um and sam harris get in it's not that
close but
um it's it's kind of uh we entered
so that's one level that's kind of
mainstream
and um
but my cosmology ultimately is what we
did on the first session
it's a modern minimalist approach you
just need three things
you need some kind of process or
movement or something happening
there has to be it has to be uh
self-differentiating
uh or the only other way to say that it
has to have
asymmetric attributes which is
self-differentiating
and the self-differentiating parts have
to participate um
if you press me that's that's the only
thing everything else is story
added to it
so um
i pretty i pretty much you know people
sometimes come to me they think i'm
kind of religious or spiritual or
mystical i'm pretty much
um yeah have that taoist notion
of um so you know this morning i was
going to write the non-duality of life
and death
so if you think of that as a cosmology
that's pretty deep i
i i i pretty much um
believe is a strong word i work toward
uh integrating that insight of the
non-duality of life and death
um i surround myself
uh with it in my daily life
it's kind of like a penance i do here at
the farm raising animals and like a
bobcat got in and killed my
duck and then i have to you know it's
like
and then i watch myself not let being
able to let that go
and then i'm reinforcing the duck stall
and the last thing i need to do
is being like cutting wood and making
new
you know and but this seems to me
to be a penis or a karmic
practice that i've settled into on a
daily basis
i saved a a fawn from
two dogs the other day
and
yeah so um it's interesting you know i'm
just kind of
noticing that i wrote that this morning
coming in
i don't know if that has something to do
with your question
yeah that's helpful i guess so if i'm
understanding you correctly you're
saying that your day-to-day experiences
on the farm sort of act as your
percepti they basically embed your
perception and then
when you're doing your inside practices
somehow you
had these three particular elements that
emerged
self-differentiation process and so on
and then
use that to formulate your cosmology
because i'm trying to see how does one
go about the process for themselves
because obviously there's no point in
copy pasting someone else's cosmology
that's not the point uh because
especially i feel like there's this
embedded cosmology of
our current society that we're living in
uh based on the the job we do and the
internet and all the inputs we consume
and i feel like that is becoming very
constraining and it's preventing me from
discovering and creating create discover
like rob says
my own formulation of it
yeah it's an interesting question um i i
um think that there's that is a paradox
uh i think we we have some impression
that there's more discourse and more um
more ways of looking at things but i
would say since the 50s
it's been really the the discourse is
very reductive
there's not there's not a lot of
tolerance for
uh ideas you know as as eric and brett
weinstein talk about um they call it
disc or something like the repression of
independent science um everything pretty
much most of this stuff is driven by
i think the economy it's the biggest
driver of these the kinds of games we
play
uh even if you don't want to play the
game it's it's not easy to play that
game
so um and i think that has
greatly it's kind of like the economy
late stage capitalism it's
centralization and monopolization
and that's kind of what the information
ecology
is really uh also being centralized and
monopolized
and the funny thing is um
it doesn't work it no longer requires
um it has a momentum of its own so it's
a lot of this discourse is socially
sanctioned it doesn't have to be
sanctioned by
uh effort from any kind of central
authority
uh that's really kind of uh
sad really um
can i ask you a follow-up question about
cosmology
[Music]
um
i have well let's see
what's the question the question is that
it seems like
there are um many different cosmologies
that sort of pervade our
[Music]
um
the the ether uh somebody like
you know richard tarniss could talk
about the
the scientific cosmology and the way
it's decentered us
from our lived experience and that's a
very like heady way to think about
it but then i noticed that most of the
time my cosmology revolves around
um like
going to work and and getting some food
um and i wondered if you could talk
about like when
uh i didn't see his name i'm sorry but
the man who was just talking about
freddie um freddy
for probably pretty when he was just
talking about
um the sort of default cosmologies i was
wondering if you could say a little bit
about what you
perceive as the the cosmology that
is sort of the if there is kind of a
default world view or
if there's maybe some different ones
that depend on
where you live or or you know your kind
of lifestyle your rural or
urban lifestyle or something like that
how do you think about
like do we have shared cosmologies
anymore
yeah so i wrote if you um i
i did a like a 35 minute video
on integral stage uh the future
faces of spirit or something like that
and in it i talk about the spirituality
we need
um and i talk about uh spirituality as a
set
of commitments uh metaphysical
cosmological
uh axiological ethics and
um
epistemological commitments and
i make the case for
moving to process ontology i think
a process ontology and then the
metaphysics
of experience so to
come from experience and perception
to a cosmology rather than
have an conceptual cosmology than that
then that then formulates the container
of your experience
so
and so one of the things so
that's there if you want to want to look
at i don't want to reproduce it's kind
of
kind of boring and conceptual as it
turns out
um fight fire with fire right
but one of the things for the psycho
technology playground that we can move
your question to is something very
this very sophisticated uh inside
practice so
bear with me here when you have a
cosmology when you're thinking of your
cosmology
when you're thinking of anything that
requires systems thinking like
you're addressing something complex
if you are reflexive about that or
metacognitive about that
you will see that you have to create
a virtual frame of reference from which
the question is coming
you know how i think on the first day
someone said when i said how do you know
you're talking to yourself and you could
see
you create a one you create a virtual
representation of yourself
talking to yourself right this is these
are virtual
uh virtual cells we can create
so when you talk about
gaia for example right we have this
let's say we have this system
that we we we talked about gaia
to talk about gaia the earth as a whole
what virtual perspective are you
occupying
not an experiential one
it's you're occupying the perspectives
as if
uh for the perspective from space
looking at gaia
right
yeah astronaut so um
so in these kinds of systems thinking
there's only a handful
of perspectives what what's that common
perspective
of these virtual
arenas of thought that
we can adopt and we need to be aware
of which one we're using in order to do
some of these very sophisticated
metacognitive
uh thinking so what is the perspective
of the privileged observer who can
see what they're studying and what
they're studying
is they're insulated from its effect
right so uh ecological
systems management had this problem when
i was
in school you know we are going to
steward the ecosystem we're going to
manage the ecosystem
and and so there's this illusion that
you're not embedded in the system
that you're studying
so that creates one type of cosmology
and there's there's many cosmologies
that
would be in in that uh-huh
and this is true for cosmology it's true
for managers who
you know change agents think they can go
into a company
and change the company without being
kind of reciprocal
kind of dynamics and stuff
yeah uh this is this is the problem
trump has he thinks he can see the whole
because he's a president
he thinks the military is something he
owns and not the expression
of the safety of this 50 states you know
he can own
he always he's always he's got this
this complex of he always virtualizes
his perspective like that
so that's that's one and the second one
is called dual causation
this is very popular in mcluhan mcloone
will say we create our systems and then
the
systems create us so in dual causation
um we understand that we're creating
the system and then we understand that
given that it's a shared context
then it creates constraints that that
create us
now in both these in both these virtual
vantage points you'll notice that some
part of the system is deanimated
in the first one everything except the
privileged observer is deanimated so
i can formally operate on it it doesn't
operate on me in the second one
you have dual causation so i take
i say i'm both an agent in the system
so i can create it so i'm operating on
it and i de-animate the system
and then i flip and say
i'm de-animated because the system is
creating my behavior
right so um if you talk if you talk
about systemic racism a lot
a lot of people use dual causation
that's the virtual
uh reality uh some people use
systemic racism from the other thing
they
they really de-animate the agent inside
the system um
you can look at these all these views
from this formula
so the net the third one is very
sophisticated
and it says um i'm embedded in the
system
and i um
my actions in the system are a source of
information about it
okay so this is a this is a
a more modern uh
the other two been around for a long
time this one's a little more modern so
i'm in the system and i'm an
agent in the system and you might say i
need to adapt or survive
and my actions in the system
is a source of information about it so
i'm not operating on the system the
system's not operating on me
all agents in the system are operating
and receiving information
from the system in their in their in in
their
uh um
so that's a different move that's an
interesting one it'd be interesting to
take these and say well what's racism
from this one you know
what's what's maybe this is about
anecdotal evidence i don't know
i haven't actually used this formula to
to track something like this
now those are all so the third one's
pretty sophisticated
it's very it's pretty new but there's
another one
um so you can re-read this
if you look up my article on medium to
trim the system
tame the mind
it's it's written for organizational
audience
but it has charts and stuff the last one
is um
so the the last one i just described is
called
uh participatory inquiry i'm
participating in inquiring
but the the new one that i actually kind
of made up
um through my own uh
kind of process that i'm exploring is
called reflexive critical reflexivity
uh in this one there is no inside and
outside so
all the other three they use the inside
outside
mental model all those vantage points
have the inside and
outside and the third one you're just
everyone's inside the system
right but this critical reflexivity
drops the inside
outside um
so there's no information to be get
gotten by
the system as if the system
inside the system there's information
and it's a kind of ongoing vigilance
of the quality of your your
participation
and the lived experience of
the dynamic participation with you
even of what we call so called inanimate
objects
this opens up
a tremendous amount of life
in your world
and i think i've said this for example
so nothing's de-animated if
i'm if i'm smelling the coffee i'm
thinking
wow millions of people a billion people
who are moved by coffee every day
and and t whole countries have gone to
war
by tea you start to have this
it's it's kind of a neo-vitalism
uh there's no real information it's just
these incredibly
uh dynamic experiences
uh you can start um
having that that can be very
psychoactive in your in your day
um
and then eventually you get to uh this
question of the non-duality of life and
death
because there's this there's this
you'll see you'll see you'll feel that
you're thinking that that that life
gets de-animated like you have this kind
of category change
so if you commit com commit to it's like
easier for me anyways to think that
dead things are animated than to
release the
uh notion that when a a living
thing is dead it's not deanimated
um so
i don't know that was a big question
that's as bad as
i got
thank you
could i just then reflect on something
that came up for me
in the kind of first half of what you're
talking about
i've been i've been watching your videos
on youtube and really enjoying them but
something that's been coming strongly
for me that resonated with what you were
talking about was
spending a lot of time and energy kind
of
absorbed in this sense-making task and
complex thinking and coming to
have some sense of relationship with
reality and what's going on
um but also that
noticing that tendency towards
feeling like i've i'm coming close to
knowing what's going on and then that
developing an illusion
of power and influence over the
and then that tension between okay
i'm making sense of what's going on and
i'm thinking more clearly about it
and then the sense of oh but what what i
think about
it will have almost zero influence on
how it plays out
and just that sense of what you said
earlier with
holding that tension if maybe this isn't
we're not the ones who are gonna
influence how it turns out i don't know
if that was clear enough but it was just
something that was coming up for me
yeah no it was very clear um this is
what in my
uh uh what the spirituality we need i
i suggest we need to you know we need to
make
our whatever spiritual oil you have you
have a commitment to certain metaphysics
and this is what i call
turn toward the metaphysics of
experience
if you think about the difference of
trying to make sense of things
sense making versus uh
experience making how can we enter into
deeper experience with
what's going on in our world uh
it it it's similar so it's taking the
sense
the the word sense and putting it
in its original location which is
sensing through
experiencing you know
um
so uh like other people sometimes i go
on rants and i usually go
on rants uh by myself
because they're horribly immature uh
but part of my rant in the sense making
space
is um
is uh what gives people the legitimacy
to author the sensing that they're
making
um and um
i think that's their experience you know
there's a lot of people in the sense
making space like
consulting there's a lot of consultants
who who never ran a business
right like like it doesn't make any
sense uh
of course it makes sense because people
don't
business owners don't really pay
attention to consultants they serve a
different function but
uh and
there's a lot of economists that
you know just have some kind of
they've read a lot about economists and
they get a sense of what the academic
discourse is on it and then they
start uh cleverly putting together
ideas and blah blah blah you know mark
blythe is a great economist he's like
they don't know what the they're
talking about you know like they don't
they don't actually know real people
they have to like pay bills and stuff
you know
um so there's a lot of people in the
sense making space talking about
community that have no friends
i'll tell you that right up front right
now i'm not gonna name names but they
have no friends
uh so um maybe they invited legitimate
authority then
on building community and liberal
politics
and blah blah blah right so
um
you don't want to be one of those people
hi bonita i wanted to um
add a kind of a question um
thanks a lot for all of the material
you've put out i've really enjoyed it in
the last few weeks we have on emerge and
the presentations and i'm working
through it and enjoying it
and i appreciate you particularly
you you mentioned before that you had a
group of women that
don't want to speak out and it reminded
me of a podcast you had with jordan
paul and daniel thorson where you guys
were
in a kind of creative generative un
space of unknowing
and it seemed like there was a high
possibility of learning
and really discovering something new
together which was beautiful and
inspiring
and then i kind of contrast that to what
you're saying earlier about
um the women who were afraid to speak
and maybe the generalized illusions
coming back at them
and i'm thinking about that generally
how do we sort of preserve our parochial
perspective or our
sense of our experience you know and one
model is like
you know i'm just nervous talking right
now
because you're judging me so i need to
work on my psychology
and like another model is you know we
need to create safe spaces
so that my parochial perspectives and
the creative generative spaces can can
grow
um but we're sort of in a land project
now and we have multiple perspectives
you know we have
some of them that we're even conscious
of these generalized solutions that are
coming in uh maybe
um normative you know
like normal uh ideas about ownership and
patriarchy and you know things uh uh
artifacts from capitalism we don't wanna
bring in so we're kind of trying to
create a discussion
we can't always get to the generative
space um
but i'm just these are some of the
things i'm wrestling with and i thought
you could help with that
um and it's related to what you're
saying before yeah so
this has been going on for almost a year
[Music]
it's a design problem uh
um you know i'm kind of like the person
that
uh
you know i'm like the person that like
makes some of these appearances and
and tells people what the back story is
like
um so it's not that
people can't like myself women can't
come up and
and and do these things it's
uh for them not so much for me
you know i like like this is a really
nice space for me but it's for them is
that they feel like they have to they
would have to adopt a false role
in order for it to be uh
beneficial to the audience i mean
like the conversations we have are way
too nuanced
uh i don't think these people are want
safe places and i don't think they're
afraid to speak
they care more about well what's the
value
what's the value of this in these spaces
um
and and we have a sense that there is a
lot of value but we don't
know how to uh produce that now i have a
crazy
uh intuition um
i think like i think there's something
about
like there's something about radio did
you do you ever listen to radio i know
young people don't listen to radio not
podcasts but radio
that's very appealing to the design of
the space because
women you know you put the radio on loud
and you just you walk around and you do
things and you get in the car to run you
and you have the radio on something like
npr but of course
npr is not like edgy here
so we were talking about like the
platform itself and have this like
fascination with
with radio like like um
um i i i even have
the idea to call it high pitch uh
high pitch because i have a high pitched
voice and i hate it you know like that's
a that's a female thing
like i never listen to myself because ah
where's that voice going
uh but also like when you give a pitch
it's you know like when you're pitching
something
uh or trying to convince someone
um so we've been like playing around
it but with it but uh
there's something that we can't see yet
you know there's something about
the design problem uh
yeah um and then
and then i you know we might like do a
beta
beta version here on the stone might be
fun
um
yeah but
um it's an interesting question
it's an interesting question years ago
they had um
integral chicks do you guys ever watch
that this is like
old old culture
and they did a really good job you know
it was
very much a woman's space without being
about women's issues you know like
there's a lot of women podcast all they
do is talk about women's issues right so
um but it but you know it didn't it
didn't last for it didn't get it didn't
get a large audience
um something about the about the
platform design
that's what we're trying to figure out
um i think you have a better
you know a lot of women voices are
really good
in produced video like you know
song dance videos they're highly
produced there's a lot of creativity
but we're trying to figure out what does
that look like
in a live kind of community space
good questions we could go on forever
but i think
we're wrapped up i just want to welcome
that up
you know that prototype that you just
mentioned bonita here at the stova
okay time for one last question if it's
got a lot of energy
all right i let's i'm going to indulge
i'm going to read one poem
uh and it has something to do with this
non-duality of life and death that did
come up and then
um we'll just end with this
so weakness
arising like the perpetual cat
at breakfast sipping cool
sweet cream
even angels need reminding
why they are born
once twice thrice
a thousand times over mommies and
daddies
babies born alive and babies born
dead the tantric dirt
rises up and swallows us all
effortlessly
this too is living
this too is dead
being here over there
is bardo
crossing over like the slip
undressing the woman in your dreams
is love
remember though not to make too much of
it
not to give it too much life and
too little death
be instead in the grass
among the flowers sifting nectar
stealing pollen out of gratitude
for the sun that great pavilion
of iridescence up there
where we look for god
you